Hi. So today, I'd like to share some works in progress.
مرحباً. فاليوم أود أن أشارككم ببعض المشاريع قيد التنفيذ.
Since we are still realizing these works,
بما أننا لانزال في طور جعل هذه المشاريع حقيقة،
we are largely working within the realm
إننا لا نزال نعمل بشكل كبير في
of intuition and mystery, still.
عالم الحدس و الغموض.
So I'm going to try and describe
لذا سوف أحاول و أصف
some of the experiences that we're looking for
بعض من التجارب التي نقوم بالنظر إليها
through each of the works.
خلال كل مشروع من المشاريع.
So the first work is called the Imperial Monochromes.
لذا أول مشروع اسمه 'أحادية الألوان الإمبراطورية'.
A viewer sort of unsuspectingly walks into the room,
يدخل المتفرج إلى الغرفة و هو تقريباً ليس لديه أي أدنى فكرة،
and catches a glimpse of these panels
و ينتبه إلى هذه اللوحات
in a messy composition on the wall.
بتركيب مبعثر على الحائط.
Within seconds, as if the panels have noticed
خلال ثواني، و كأن اللوحات قد لاحظت
the presence of the viewer,
وجود المتفرج،
they appear to panic and sort of get into
يبدوا أنها تهلع و تصطف
a strict symmetry.
بتناسق منضبط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So this is the sketch of the two states.
إذاً هذا رسم للحالتين.
One is total chaos. The other is absolute order.
إحداها بفوضى عارمة. الأخرى بترتيب كلي.
And we were interested in seeing how little change
و كنا مهتمين برؤية بساطة التغير
it takes to move from one state to the other state.
الذي يلزمه الأمر للتحول من حالة إلى الأخرى.
This also reminded us of two very different pictorial traditions.
هذا أيضاً يذكرنا باثنين مختلفين جداً من التقاليد التصويرية.
One is the altar tablets of the 15th century,
إحداها هي لوحات المذبح في القرن الـ 15،
and the other is about 100 years ago,
و التقليد الثاني عمره حوالي 100 سنة،
Malevich's abstract compositions.
تركيبات ماليفيتش التجريدية.
So I'm just going to take you to a video.
إذاً سوف آخذكم لمشاهدة فيديو.
To give you a sense of scale,
لأعطيكم فكرة عن المقياس،
the largest panel is about two meters high.
إن ارتفاع أكبر لوحة هو حوالي مترين.
That's about this much. And the smallest one is an A4.
ذلك تقريباً بهذا الارتفاع. و أصغر واحدة بحجم A4 [ورقة طابعة عادية].
So a viewer enters the space,
إذاً يدخل المتفرج إلى الحيز،
and they snap to attention.
و بسرعة تنتبه اللوحات.
And after a while, if the viewer continues
و بعد مدة، إن استمر المتفرج
to remain in the space,
في مكانه بالحيز،
the panels will sort of become immune
سوف تصبح اللوحات نوع ما منيعة
to the presence of the viewer
لوجود المتفرج
and become lax and autonomous again,
و تصبح مرتخية و فردية مرة أخرى،
until they sort of sense a presence in the room or a movement,
حتى تشعر بوجود في الغرفة أو البيئة،
when they will again snap to attention.
حيث سوف تنتبه بسرعة مرة أخرى.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So here it appears as if it's the viewer
فهنا تبدو و كأنه المتفرج
that's sort of instigating the sense of order among the panels,
هو من يبعث على الشعور بالترتيب في اللوحات،
but it could also be the other way around,
لكن قد يكون الأمر بالعكس،
that the panels are so stuck within
أن اللوحات عالقة في
their preconditioned behaviors
تصرفاتها المكتسبة
that they sort of thrust the viewer with the role of a tyrant.
بحيث تقوم بفرض على المتفرج دور الطاغية.
So this brings me to a quieter, small work
فهذا يحضرني إلى مشروع أكثر هدوءاً و أصغر
called Handheld.
يسمى بـ 'المحمول باليد'.
The viewer sees a piece of paper
يرى المتفرج قطعة من الورق
that's mounted on the far end of the wall,
مثبته على الطرف البعيد من الحائط،
but when you go closer, you see that it's a blank
لكن عندما تقترب، ترى أنها ورقة فارغة
A4, or a letter-sized piece of paper,
بحجم A4، أو قطعة ورق بحجم ورقة الرسالة،
that's held on either side
المحمولة من الطرفين
by two small hands
بواسطة يدين صغيرتين
that appear to be carved with a great deal
اللتان تبدوان منحوتتان بتفاصيل
of attention and care from a small block of wood.
و عناية دقيقة من مكعب صغير من الخشب.
The viewer also sees that this entire sculpture
إن المتفرج أيضاً يرى أن هذه المنحوتة بأكملها
is sort of moving very slightly,
تتحرك بشكل طفيف نوع ما،
as if these two hands are trying
و كأن هتان اليدين تحاولان
to hold the paper very still
حمل الورقة بثبات كبير
for a long period of time,
لمدة طويلة من الزمن،
and somehow are not managing to.
و بطريقة ما لا تستطيعان فعل ذلك.
So this instability in the movement
إذاً عدم الثبات هذا بالحركة
very closely resembles the unsteady nature
يشابه كثيراً الطبيعة المهتزة
of images seen through a handheld camera.
للصور التي نراها من خلال الكاميرات المحمولة باليد.
So here I'm going to show you two tandem clips.
لذا هنا سوف أريكم مقطعين مترادفين.
One is through a still camera
أحدهما من خلال كاميرا ثابتة
and the other is through a handheld camera.
و الآخر من خلال كاميرا محمولة باليد.
And you immediately see how the unsteady nature
و أنت ترى فوراً كيف أن الطبيعة المهتزة
of the video suggests the presence
للفيديو تدل على وجود
of an observer and a subjective point of view.
مشاهد و على وجهة نظر شخصية.
So we've just removed the camera
فنحن فقط أزلنا الكاميرا
and transferred that movement onto the panel.
و نقلنا تلك الحركة إلى اللوحة.
So here's a video.
فهذا فيديو.
You have to imagine the other hand. It's not there yet.
عليكم تخيل اليد الأخرى. إنها ليست هناك بعد.
But to us, we're sort of trying to evoke
لكن بالنسبة لنا، نحن نحاول نوع ما أن نثير
a self-effacing gesture, as if there's a little person
الشعور بإيماءة خجولة، و كأنه هناك شخص صغير
with outstretched arms
مع يدين ممدودتين
behind this enormous piece of paper.
خلف قطعة الورق الهائلة هذه.
That sort of likens it to the amount of strain
هذا يمثل نوع ما حجم الضغط
to be at the service of the observer and present
الناتج عن خدمة المتفرج و عن عرض
this piece of paper very delicately to the viewer
هذه القطعة من الورق بشكل دقيق جداً
in front of them.
أمام المتفرج.
The next work is Decoy.
المشروع الآخر هو 'الطُعم'.
This is a cardboard model, so the object
هذا نموذج كرتوني، فالغرض
is about as tall as I am.
بنفس ارتفاعي تقريباً.
It has a rounded body, two arms,
لديه جسم مكور، ذراعان،
and a very tall, head-like antenna,
و هوائي كالرأس، طويل جداً،
and its sole purpose is to attract attention towards itself.
و هدفه الوحيد هو جذب الانتباه لنفسه.
So when a viewer passes by,
لذا عندما يمر متفرج،
it sort of tilts from side to side,
إنه نوع ما يميل من جانب إلى آخر،
and moves its arms more and more frantically
و يحرك ذراعيه بهوجاء متزايدة
as the person gets closer.
مع اقتراب الشخص أكثر.
So here is the first test scenario.
فهكذا هو أول اختبار.
You see the two movements integrated,
ترى أن الحركتين متداخلتان،
and the object seems to be employing
و يبدو أن الغرض يشارك
its entire being in this expression of desperation.
بجسمه كله بتعبيره هذا عن يأسه.
But the idea is that once it's got the person's attention,
لكن الفكرة هي أنه عندما يحصل على انتباه الشخص،
it's no longer interested, and it looks for the next person whose attention to get.
يفقد الاهتمام، و يبدأ بالبحث عن الشخص التالي لجذب انتباهه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So this is the final fabricated body of the Decoy.
إذاً هذا هو المجسم النهائي المكسو لـ 'الطعم'.
It appears to be mass-manufactured
يبدو و كأنه تم انتاج منه كميات كبيرة
like it came out of a factory
كأنه قد خرج من مصنع
like vacuum cleaners and washing machines.
مثل المكنسات الكهربائية و الغسالات.
Because we are always working
لأننا نعمل دائماً
from a very personal space,
من مساحة شخصية جداً،
we like how this consumer aesthetic
نحن نحب كيف عنصر المستهلك الجمالي هذا
sort of depersonalizes the object
يقوم بإزالة طابع الشخصية عن الغرض نوع ما
and gives us a bit of distance
و يعطينا القليل من المساحة
in its appearance, at least.
بشكله، على الأقل.
And so to us this is a kind of sinister being
و هكذا بالنسبة لنا هذا نوع من الكائنات الشريرة
which is trying to distract you from the things
الذي يحاول أن يشتت انتباهك عن الأمور
that actually need your attention,
التي تحتاج إليه بالفعل،
but it could also be a figure that needs a lot of help.
لكنه قد يكون شخصية تحتاج إلى الكثير من المساعدة.
The next work is an object,
إن المشروع التالي هو غرض،
that's also a kind of sound instrument.
الذي هو أيضاً نوع من الآلات الصوتية.
In the shape of an amphitheater
على هيئة مدرج
that's scaled to the size of an audience
الذي حجمه يمثل حجم الجمهور
as perceived from somebody from the stage.
كما يبدو لشخص من على المسرح.
So from where I'm standing,
إذاً من مكاني هذا،
each of you appears to be this big,
كل شخص منكم يبدو بهذا الحجم،
and the audience sort of takes the entire
و يأخذ الجمهور نوع ما
field of my vision.
كل مجال رؤيتي.
Seated in this audience are 996 small figures.
في هذا الجمهور 996 شكل صغير.
They're mechanically enabled to clap
إنها قادرة ميكانيكاً على التصفيق
of their own free will.
بإرادتها الذاتية.
This means that each of them can decide
الأمر الذي يعني أن كل واحدة منها يمكنها أن تقرر
if and when they want to clap,
إن كانت و متى تريد أن تصفق،
how hard, for how long,
و درجة التصفيق، و مدته،
how they want to be influenced by those around them or influence others,
و كيف تريد أن تتأثر بما حولها أو كيف تريد أن تؤثر بالآخرين،
and if they want to contribute to innovation.
و إن كانت تريد أن تشارك بالابتكار.
So when the viewer steps in front of the audience,
فعندنا يقف المتفرج أمام الجمهور،
there will be a response.
سوف يكون هناك ردة فعل.
It could be a few claps or a strong applause,
قد تكون بضع تصفيقات أو تصفيق حار،
and then nothing happens until the viewer
و لن يحدث أي شي بعد ذلك حتى يترك
leaves the stage, and again the audience will respond.
المتفرج المسرح، و مرة أخرى سوف يستجيب الجمهور.
It could be anything from a few feeble claps
قد تتراوح ردة الفعل من بضع تصفيقات ضعيفة
from members in the audience,
من أفراد من الجمهور،
or it could be a very loud ovation.
أو قد تكون هتاف صاخب جداً.
So to us, I think we're really looking
فبالنسبة لنا، أعتقد أننا حقاً ننظر
at an audience as its own object
إلى جمهور على أنه شيء لذاته
or its own organism
أو فيه كان حي خاص به
that's also got a sort of musical-like quality to it,
الذي له أيضاً خاصية موسيقية نوعاً ما،
an instrument.
آلة موسيقية.
So the viewer can play it
فالمتفرج يمكنه العزف عليها
by eliciting quite complex and varied,
بإثارة أنماط صوتية أو موسيقية
nuanced musical or sound patterns,
دقيقة معقدة جداً و مختلفة،
but cannot really provoke the audience
لكنه لا يمكنه إثارة الجمهور
into any particular kind of response.
ليقوم بأي نوع من ردة الفعل.
So there's a sense of judgment and capriciousness
إذاً هناك شعور بالحكم و المزاجية
and uneasiness involved.
و بالتوتر في الأمر.
It also has an alluring and trap-like quality to it.
و للأمر خاصية تألق و خديعة.
So here if you see we're quite excited about
فهنا ترى أننا متحمسين كثيراً بخصوص
the image of the head splitting to form the two hands.
صورة الرأس الذي ينقسم ليمثل اليدين.
So here's a small visual animation,
فهنا توضيح رسومي مرئي بسيط،
as if the two sides of the brain are sort of clashing
كأن جانبي الدماغ يتضاربان
against each other to kind of make sense
مع بعضهما البعض ليعطيان شعور
of the duality and the tension.
بالثنائية و الشدّة.
And here is a prototype.
و هنا نموذج مبدئي.
So we can't wait to be engulfed by 996 of them.
فنحن لا نطيق الانتظار حتى نحاط بـ 996 واحدة منها.
Okay, this is the last work. It's called the Framerunners.
حسناً، هذا آخر مشروع. اسمه الـ 'عدائي الإطار'.
It comes out of the idea of a window.
إن الفكرة عن نافذة.
This is an actual window in our studio,
هذه نافذة حقيقية بالاستديو الخاص بنا،
and as you can see, it's made up of three
و كما ترون، إنها مصنوع من ثلاثة
different thicknesses of wooden sections.
سماكات من قطع الخشب.
So we used the same window vocabulary
لذا فقد استخدمنا نفس مفردات النافذة
to construct our own frame or grid
لصنع الإطار أو الشبكة الخاصة بنا
that's suspended in the room and that can
المعلقة في الغرفة و التي يمكن
be viewed from two sides.
رؤيتها من الجانبين.
This grid is inhabited by a tribe of small figures.
إن الشبكة مسكونة بقبيلة من الأشكال الصغيرة.
They're also made up of three different sizes,
إنها أيضاً مصنوعة من ثلاثة أحجام مختلفة،
as if to suggest a kind of perspective
كأنها توحي بنوع من المنظور
or landscape on the single plain.
أو المنظر في البُعد الواحد.
Each of these figures can also run backward
كل من هذه الأشكال يمكنه أيضاً الجري إلى الوراء
and forward in the track
و إلى الأمام في المسار
and hide behind two adjacent tracks.
و أن يختبئ خلف مسارين متجاورين.
So in contrast to this very tight grid,
لذا على النقيض من هذه الشبكة المحكمة،
we wanted to give these figures a very comical
أردنا أن نعطي هذه الأشكال صفة
and slapstick-like quality,
كوميدية جداً و تهريجية،
as if a puppeteer has taken them
كأن محرك الدمى قد أخذها
and physically animated them down the path.
و حركها فعلياً على المسار.
So we like the idea of these figures
إذاً نحن نحب فكرة تحرك
sort of skipping along
هذه الأشكال على طول المسار
like they're oblivious and carefree
كأنها غافلة و مبتهجة
and happy-go-lucky and content,
و سعيدة و راضية،
until they sort of sense a movement from the viewer
إلى أن تشعر بنوع من الحركة من المتفرّج
and they will hide behind the fastest wall.
و سوف تختبئ خلف أسرع حائط.
So to us, this work also presents its own contradiction.
لذا بالنسبة لنا، هذا العمل يمثل أيضاً التناقض المتضمن فيه.
These figures are sort of entrapped
هذه الأشكال نوع ما محبوسة
within this very strong grid,
في هذه الشبكة القوية جداً،
which is like a prison, but also a fortress,
و التي هي سجن، لكنها أيضاً قلعة،
because it allows them to be oblivious
لأنها تسمح للأشكال بأن تكون غافلة
and naive and carefree and quite oblivious
و ساذجة و مبتهجة و غافلة جداً
of the external world.
عن العالم الخارجي.
So all these real life qualities that I talk about
فكل هذه الخصائص الواقعية التي أتكلم عنها
are sort of translated to a very specific
هي مترجمة إلى تشكيل
technical configuration,
تقني محدد جداً،
and we were very lucky to collaborate
و كنا محظوظين جداً للتعاون
with ETH Zurich to develop the first prototype.
مع جامعة إي تي إتش زيورخ لتطوير أول نموذج مبدئي.
So you see they extracted the motion cogs
فترى أنهم قد استخلصوا التروس الحركية
from our animations and created a wiggle
من رسومنا و صنعوا تذبذب
that integrated the head-bobbing movement
الذي دمج حركة الرأس المطأطئة
and the back-and-forth movement.
مع الحركة للأمام و للوراء.
So it's really quite small.
فهي حقاً صغيرة جداً.
You can see it can fit into the palm of my hand.
يمكنك أن تراها تتسع في راحة يدي.
So imagine our excitement when we saw it
فتخيل تحمسنا عندما رأيناها
really working in the studio, and here it is.
تعمل بالفعل بالاستديو، و ها هي هنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)